in addition to different Mis rates
depending on whether we are looking
globally or locally at a cach in a
multi-level cache we have what is called
an inclusion property the inclusion
property has to do with assuming that
the block is in level one cache is it
that it may or may not be in the level
two cache or it has to be in the L2
cache and it is also possible to make a
system in which if a block is in one it
cannot be also in L2 this is often
called exclusion this is what we usually
call
inclusion and this doesn't have a name
it's neither exclusion nor
inclusion so if we just have a normal
cach hierarchy where processor accesses
go to level one cache and then the
misses from that go to a larger level
two cache the question is what will we
get and the answer is unless we
explicitly try to en Force inclusion or
exclusion we will get this most of the
stuff that is in L1 will also be found
in L2 but there is no guarantee for that
so there could be blocks in L1 that have
been replaced from L2 let's look at a
simple example when the L1 cache has two
blocks and is fully associative and the
larger level two cache has four blocks
and is fully associative and both of
them use lru policy now let's suppose
that the procor access is block a it's
going to be a miss here and a miss here
it's brought from memory placed here and
then that is fed to the L1 cache so it
places it here so so far we have
inclusion let's now access Block B it
gets brought from memory here and here
we still have inclusion if we now access
Block C it will be here and here and we
still have inclusion but let's suppose
that when we had the blocks A and B
brought in we reais a that is going to
be a level one hit so now the lru
counters in level one are this but
because there has been no access when a
was re accessed to level two cuz it was
a level one hit so we don't go to
L2 here we still have that b is the most
recently accessed a is the next most
recently accessed and let's say these
two are like this now let's say we
access C what's going to happen is we
have a Miss in the L1 cache we have a
Miss in the L2 cache we bring in C and
replace the least recently used block
which is this the counters now get
updated to be three 2 1 and zero and the
counters and then C is brought into this
level one cache and replaces B because
that's the least recently used block and
the counters become one and zero here
now let's say a is accessed again that
changes the counters back to this and
there is no access to the level two
cache let's say now we access block D
it's going to be fetched here the
counters are updated to three 2 1 and z
and d is also brought into the level one
cache and placed here of course that
updates the counters this way now let's
say a is accessed again now we have the
counters again one Zer let's say now e
is accessed
it's a Miss in both caches we bring e in
and now in the L2 cache it replaces the
least recently used block which is a
however in the L1 cache it will replace
the least recently used block which is D
so at this point we no longer have
inclusion because a is in the L1 cache
but is no longer found in the L2 cache
so inclusion does not necessarily hold
when you have a cash hierarchy because
things that are frequently accessed in
the L1 cache will not be frequently
maybe accessed in L2 because all of the
accesses to that block are going to L1
and the L2 never sees them So eventually
that block gets replaced from L2 to
maintain inclusion properly we have to
have a so-called inclusion bit added to
L2 which is one if that block is also in
L1 and when we replace things from L2 to
we prevent blocks whose inclusion bit is
one from being replaced that ensures
that we never replace something that is
still in L1 so we can maintain inclusion
but again that requires an additional
bit